Finding Aid for Daniel E. Atkins papers, 1959-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Daniel E. Atkins papers 1959-2011 1985-2004
Atkins, Daniel E. (Daniel Ewell)
2012139 Aa2
Vice President for Research Cyberinfrastructure at the University of Michigan, dean of the School of Information, Interim Dean and Associate Dean for Research at the College of Engineering. Papers include materials relating to research in technologically-based collaboration, institutional leadership, teaching and service.
11.6 linear feet
192.5 MB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (Donor No. 10549 ) and digital materials were accessioned in 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is restricted until July 1, 2021 and then open without restriction. Records may be accessed with the permission of Daniel Atkins before July 1, 2021.
Daniel Ewell Atkins III graduated magna cum laude with a B.S. in Electrical Engineering from Bucknell University in 1965. While a student, he helped form and eventually became director of the first Bucknell computing center supporting an IBM 1620 and edited The Bucknell Engineer. He went on to study at the University of Illinois, working with James Robertson on methods for selection of quotient digits during digital division, and received his M.S. in Electrical Engineering in 1967 and a PhD in 1970. After graduation, he served for six years as a captain of military intelligence in the U.S. Army Reserve.
Atkins joined the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan in the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science in 1972. Initially his research focused on the development of high-performance computer architecture, including work on some of the earliest parallel computers. He collaborated with the Mayo Clinic on development of computer-assisted tomography (CAT) and worked to develop improved arithmetic algorithms. Some of his work in higher-radix division has been widely used in commercial machines, including the Intel Pentium series.
At the College of Engineering, Atkins chaired the committee that established one of the earliest undergraduate computer engineering degree programs. He served as the Associate Dean for Research between October 1981 and December 1988 and was the Interim Dean of the college between January 1989 and August 1990. Between 1985 and 1989 he was the project director of the National Science Foundation (NSF) funded EXPRES project, which laid the foundation for the NSF's FastLane system for conducting NSF business over the Internet. During this period, his research focus began to shift from traditional computer architecture to distributed knowledge environments, and understanding new ways of doing knowledge-based activities. In collaboration with psychology professors Gary and Judy Olson, political science professor Michael Cohen and others, and intrigued by the emerging convergence of computing and communication systems, he began to engage with digital libraries and collaboratories. "Collaboratories" as defined by Atkins and his colleagues, were spaces where researchers could work without regard to physical location, interacting with colleagues, and accessing instrumentation, information and data.
In July 1992, he became dean of the School of Information and Library Studies and led the school through its transformation into the School of Information (SI). SI was the first of the "information schools" aimed at preparing information professionals ready to engage with people-centered systems and institutions. While dean, Atkins was project director of the $8 million U-M Digital Library Project (1992-1997) and helped pilot the Mellon-sponsored JSTOR Project (1992-1995). He was also director of the $5 million NSF-sponsored Upper Atmospheric Research Collaboratory (UARC) (1992-1998), which was renewed in 1998 for three more years under the broader name Space Physics and Aeronomy Research Collaboratory (SPARC).
Under Atkin's leadership, the W.K. Kellogg Foundation funded research to support the transformation of the School of Information and Library Science into the School of Information in the CRISTAL-ED project (Coalition on Reinventing Information Science, Technology and Library Education). Beginning in 1997, Atkins formed and directed a Kellogg-supported Alliance for Community Technology (ACT) to support the use of information technology in service of broader participation in civil society. Another outreach program, the Community Information Corps (CIC), matched SI students with public interest work in a for-credit course, sometimes led by Atkins himself. He has also served as a consultant to Kellogg on the innovative use of information and communication technology for enriching education opportunities for at risk youth in the U.S., and for both rural communities and higher education in southern Africa.
Stepping down as dean of SI in 2002, Atkins served as Chair of NSF's Blue-Ribbon Advisory Panel on Cyberinfrastructure. In early 2003, the panel issued a highly influential report, "Revolutionizing Science and Engineering Through Cyberinfrastructure." Cyberinfrastructure is the IT structure that enables scientific inquiry. It includes computing cycles, networking, massive storage and managed information, measurement tools, shared standards and applications for scientific computation. It also focuses on sharing, collaboration and efficiency. The panel's report, now dubbed "The Atkins Report," received international attention and has served as a guide for strategic planning in academia and research funding agencies. In 2006, Atkins was named to head NSF's newly created Office of Cyberinfrastructure.
Returning to U-M in September 2008, the regents named Atkins the W.K. Kellogg Professor of Community Information (SI's first endowed chair) and appointed him Associate Vice President for Research Cyberinfrastructure, directing the Office of Research Cyberinfrastructure (ORCI). ORCI's mission is to match researchers with advanced computing resources. It provides services such as high-performance computing, cloud computing, a software library, data management, visualization, collaboration and instructional tools.
In addition, Atkins served on panels of the US National Academies exploring such issues as scholarship in the digital age, the future of scholarly communication, and the impact of information technology on the future of higher education. He was a consultant to the International Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development and to the American Council of Learned Societies. Atkins is co-author (with James Duderstadt and Doug Van Houweling) of the 2002 book Higher Education in the Digital Age: Technology Issues and Strategies for American Colleges and Universities.
The Daniel E. Atkins papers document his research and administrative roes at the University of Michigan. The papers include materials relating to research in technologically-based collaboration, institutional leadership, teaching and service,including meetings and activities as Dean of the School of Information. The papers comprise 11.6 linear feet in three major series: University of Illinois, U-M College of Engineering, and U-M School of Information. In addition, there is a digital series related to Atkins' work on the U-M IT Council.
Subjects:
Atkins, Daniel E. (Daniel Ewell); Information technology.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Experimental Research in Electronic Submission Project.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Information.
- University of Illinois 1959-1972
  The small University of Illinois series, 1959-1972 (0.1 lin. ft.) documents Atkins' training in computer science and his work with ILLIAC.
  [Restricted until July 1 2021 ]
  - EE 394 Computer Arithmetic undated (Box 1)
  - ILLIAC II Main Arithmetic Unit 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - ILLIAC III Documentation 1965 (Box 1)
  - ILLIAC IV Arithmetic 1967 (Box 1)
  - Robertson, James E. 1958-1965 (Box 1)
  - Soceneatu, Aurel 1969-1972 (Box 1)
- U-M College of Engineering 1976-1992
  The U-M College of Engineering series, 1976-1992 (3.5 lin. ft.) relates to Atkins' early career at the University of Michigan, and is divided into four subseries. The first subseries, Topical, 1976-1992 (1.1 lin. ft.), contains alphabetically arranged subject files related to Atkins's tenure at the College of Engineering. Researchers should note the files named "Chronological Activities" which document Atkins' meetings, trips, talks and social events, arranged chronologically. Eight folders of "Correspondence" are also located in this series. The second subseries, EXPRES project, 1986-1990 (0.9 lin. ft.) supplements materials accessioned earlier in the Gary M. Olson papers and in the College of Engineering Record Group related to Atkins project when he was Associate Dean of Research. Files are arranged alphabetically. The third subseries, High performance computing, 1991-1992 (0.2 lin. ft.) documents a collaboration among the University of Michigan, auto manufacturers and national laboratories. Files are arranged alphabetically. Lastly, the subseries, Other projects, 1984-1992 (1.5 lin. ft.) contains grant proposals and research projects, arranged alphabetically.
  - Topical 1976-1992
    - Advanced Infotech Environment Capital Campaign 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Bibshare 1990 (Box 1)
    - Briefing and tour for College of Engineering deans Center for Information Technology (CITI) 1987 (Box 1)
    - Calendar 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Chronological activities 1984-1985, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL) 1990 (Box 1)
    - Collaboratory workshop 1988 (Box 1)
    - Computer Aided Engineering Network (CAEN) 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Computer, Information and Control Engineering (CICE) 569: Digital Computer Arithmetic 1981 (Box 1)
    - Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1987-1988, 1990-1992, 8 folders (Box 1)
      (Note that the missing dates correspond to interim deanship)
    - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (EECS), 1990-2 (Box 1)
    - EECS 598-5: Advanced Systems Architecture Video Computing 1991 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Retreat 1985 (Box 1)
    - IBM Proposal 1988 (Box 1)
    - Information Technology Architecture Committee, 1986-7 (Box 2)
    - Information Technology Policy Committee, 1990-2 (Box 2)
    - Interim deanship 1990 (Box 2)
    - Intelligent Vehicle Highway System Education Program (IVHS) 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Laboratory for Scientific Computation (LaSC) 1991 (Box 2)
    - Manufacturing Strategic Plan and Technology Exchange Program 1992 (Box 2)
    - Mayo Clinic -- Computer Tomography (CT), 1976-79 (Box 2)
    - Personal goals / perspective 1991 (Box 2)
    - Reports on automation in U-M Libraries 1983 (Box 2)
    - Rolodex Master List 1990 (Box 2)
    - University Computing Policy Committee 1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Vendor index 1992 (Box 2)
    - Viewgraphs relating to the college, 1984-8 (Box 2)
    - Visitors hosted 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Project, 1986-90
    - ArborText subcontract 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - BBN Laboratories subcontract 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - Budget 1986 (Box 2)
    - Carnegie Mellon proposal 1986 (Box 2)
    - CMU ODA Tool Kit Site Installation Guide 1988 (Box 2)
    - Diamond Users Reference Guide 1985 (Box 2)
    - EXPRES Advisory Committee Meeting Briefing Book 1987 (Box 2)
    - EXPRES Advisory Committee Meeting Briefing Book 1988 (Box 2)
    - EXPRES Advisory Committee Meeting Supplementary Material 1988 (Box 2)
    - IBM draft subcontract 1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1986-9, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - NSF grant agreements, 1986-8 (Box 2)
    - NSF reports on electronic submission of proposals, 1982-6 (Box 2)
    - Project chron 1988 (Box 3)
    - Supporting Collaboration with Advanced Multimedia Electronic Mail: The NSF EXPRES Project 1989 (Box 3)
    - Wrap up and final budget 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - High Performance Computing 1991-1992
    - Application of High Performance Computing to Automotive Design and Manufacturing 1992 (Box 3)
    - Argonne National Lab 1992 (Box 3)
    - Chrysler, Ford, GM 1992 (Box 3)
    - College of Engineering Capabilities re: Automotive 1992 (Box 3)
    - High Performance Computing Committee (HPCC) Correspondence 1992 (Box 3)
    - HPCC Meetings 1992 (Box 3)
    - Los Alamos National Laboratory Capabilities 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - National Computing Consortium for Advanced Automotive Engineering (NCCAAE) 1992 (Box 3)
    - Vendors 1992 (Box 3)
    - Viewgraphs 1992 (Box 3)
  - Other projects 1984-1992
    - Acquisition of Massively Parallel Processors for Scientific Computing Applications and Computing Science Proposal 1992 (Box 3)
    - AT&T Grant Proposal to Support an Integrated Networked Video Computing Workstation Facility 1991 (Box 3)
    - Center for Collaboration Science and Technology (CCST) 1988 (Box 3)
    - CCST Proposal 1988 (Box 3)
    - Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI) 1985 (Box 3)
    - Center for Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing (CRIM) 1985 (Box 3)
    - CIESIN Data and Research Center (CDRC) (Consortium for International Earth Science Information Network) 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Collaboratory" Miscellaneous 1989-1992 (Box 3)
    - College of Engineering collaboration with Technical Industry 1982-1989 (Box 3)
    - Computer-Aided Engineering Network (CAEN) 1985 (Box 3)
    - Content-based video access 1986-1991 (Box 3)
    - Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC) Flagship Proposal 1990-1991, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Electronic Information Services (EIS) Project 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Electronic Library for Collaboration (ELCO) Project 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Engineering Research Center (ERC) 1984 (Box 3)
    - Fluent Project 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Collaboration System (MCS) 1988 (Box 4)
    - Multimedia and Network Research 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - National Engineering Information Service (NENGIS) 1992 (Box 4)
    - Nortel Project 1991 (Box 4)
    - NSF CISE II: Building the Collaboratory: A Coordinated Experiment in Research in Advanced Interactive Group Environments Proposal 1991 (Box 4)
    - NSF CISE II: Proposal creation 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - NSF CISE II: Site visit 1992 (Box 4)
    - NSF Coordination Theory and Collaboration Technology Workshop 1991 (Box 4)
    - NSF: Technology Support for Collaborative Workgroups Progress Report 1990 (Box 4)
    - NSF: Technology Support for Collaborative Workgroups Proposal 1988 (Box 4)
    - NSF: Technology Support for Collaborative Workgroups Proposal 1992 (Box 4)
    - NSF Workshop: Towards a National Collaboratory 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Personal Productivity Project 1984, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Proposal for Massively Parallel Processor (MPP) at U-M 1992 (Box 4)
    - Sun DIME/COCO Project 1991 (Box 4)
    - U-M Collaboratory Initiative 1991 (Box 4)
    - U-M/UMI Document Retrieval Network Server Proposal 1988 (Box 4)
    - UMI Partnership 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Verity TOPIC 1991 (Box 4)
- U-M School of Information 1991-2006
  The U-M School of Information series, 1991-1992006 (7.8 lin. ft.) relates to Atkins tenure there, as professor and dean. It consists of seven subseries. The first, Meetings and activities 1991-2002 (2.9 lin. ft.) is arranged chronologically. Each file documents an event in Atkins' schedule, though many of the files contain little content. Titles of talks given by Atkins are given in quotes in the folder titles. While occasionally the text of the talk is available, more often only images of the slides have been preserved. In 1997, Atkins' assistant created a binder for all events instead of creating a file for each event. The contents of this binder are in the folders labeled "Activities chron." The second subseries, Topical, 1992-2006 (2.5 lin. ft.) contains subject files relating to the conception and development of the School of Information, information-related professional organizations, and academic programs. In addition there is some biographical information contained in folders prefixed Atkins.
  The third subseries under the SI series relates to the Digital Library Program, 1994-2000 (0.6 lin. ft.). Wendy Lougee, who was the director of the Digital Library Program, and later the Associate Director for Digital Library Services, prepared a briefing book for Atkins for the Digital Library Program, and the contents are contained in this series. Materials are presented in chronological order and comprise correspondence, meetings with "3D's" (Dan Atkins, Don Riggs, Doug Van Howeling) and color transparencies for talks. The fourth SI subseries, Kellogg Foundation, 1995-2001 (0.8 lin. ft.) contains materials related to Kellogg-funded projects, arranged alphabetically. The fifth subseries, Other funders, 1992-2001 (0.4 lin. ft.) includes files documenting research projects and project proposals to the National Science Foundation (NSF), Ameritech, and Industrial Partners of Computer Science and Engineering (IPoSCE). The sixth subseries, Alliance for Community Technology (ACT), 1991-1998 (0.2 lin. ft.) contains files created by Katherine Willis who managed ACT under Atkins' direction. Finally, the seventh SI subseries, Community Information Corps, 2001-2005 (0.4 lin. ft.) consists of files created by Peter Keller-Transburg related to his staffing the Community Information Corps (CIC) at the School of Information.
  - Meetings and activities 1991-2002 (in chronological order)
    - Kellogg Symposium on Specialization in Library / Information Science Education 1991 (Box 4)
    - DARPA Manufacturing Automation and Design Environment Conference 1992 (Box 4)
    - Industrial Technology Institute (ITI): Knowledge Infrastructure Engineering 1992 (Box 4)
    - American Library Association (ALA) in San Francisco 1992 (Box 4)
    - Delivery of Engineering Education: Applying Emerging Technologies: NRC planning meeting 1992 (Box 4)
    - CICNet Fall Joint Meeting "Why not go for the big win?," 1992 (Box 4)
    - High Performance Computing Committee (HPCC) 1992 (Box 4)
    - American Society for Information Science (ASIS) in Pittsburgh 1992 (Box 4)
    - "The University of Michigan Strategy for High Performance Computing and Visualization Environment" 1992 (Box 4)
    - "SILS Challenge and Opportunity" 1993 (Box 4)
    - Association of American Universities (AAU) Research Libraries Project, Chicago 1993 (Box 4)
    - "Information Technology and Organizational Forms: A Framework for the IT Side" 1993 (Box 4)
    - ALA in Denver "Remarks" 1993 (Box 4)
    - DRDA Project "Situation to Date" 1993 (Box 4)
    - Sony and Apple partnership "SILS Mission" 1993 (Box 4)
    - Brown Bag "Future Information Systems and Services" 1993 (Box 4)
    - Media Curriculum Meeting with Carolyn, David, Maurita, Leslie 1993 (Box 4)
    - W. David Penniman visit to SILS 1993 (Box 4)
    - Goldenberg / Van Houweling "Future of Data-Information Resources for Social Science and Research" 1993 (Box 4)
    - OCLC Visit "Towards a national collaboratory: Why not go for the big win?" 1993 (Box 4)
    - ASIS National Digital Library Meeting, Knoxville 1993 (Box 4)
    - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM) "Advanced Infrastructure Initiatives at the University of Michigan" 1993 (Box 5)
    - Meeting with Regent Phillip Power "University of Michigan SILS: Strategic Directions Review of Year 1 and Critical Needs" 1993 (Box 5)
    - NSF / ARPA Digital Library Initiative 1993 (Box 5)
    - ONLINE '93 "Digital Libraries: Visions and Realities" 1993 (Box 5)
    - SILS Homecoming "The role of ILS Education for the 21st Century" at the Ford Library 1993 (Box 5)
    - SILS Faculty Retreat 1993, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - UM Donor Breakfast in Ehrlicher Room "Vision of a 21st Century Information Infrastructure" 1993 (Box 5)
    - ASIS in Columbus 1993 (Box 5)
    - ALA in Los Angeles 1994 (Box 5)
    - IMAGIN Forum Keynote 1994 (Box 5)
    - American Research Libraries (ARL): "Educating ILS Professionals for the Day After Tomorrow" 1994 (Box 5)
    - ASIS in Portland 1994 (Box 5)
    - "A Proposal to Establish the University of Michigan Institute / School of Information and Collaboration Systems" 1994 (Box 5)
    - ALA Teleconference downlink at SILS 1994 (Box 5)
    - Association of Graduate Schools at Madison, WI 1994 (Box 5)
    - Telecommunications Policy Research Conference, Solomons, MD (canceled) 1994 (Box 5)
    - Industrial Technical Info. Mgr. Group "Frameworks for the future Digital Libraries, Collaboratories and Knowledge Management Models" 1994 (Box 5)
    - ASIS in Alexandria, VA 1994 (Box 5)
    - Association of American Medical Colleges (AAMC) in Boston "Frameworks for the future" 1994 (Box 5)
    - MIT Library Advisory Committee with Chuck Vest in Boston 1994 (Box 5)
    - Conference on Information and Knowledge Management -- National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), Gaithersburg, MD 1994 (Box 5)
    - Hawaii International Conference on System Science 1995 (Box 5)
    - ALISE and ALA at Philadelphia 1995 (Box 5)
    - Information Industry Association (IIA) Board Meeting, Sea Island, GA 1995 (Box 5)
    - Public librarians "New Library Systems and Services and Professional Education for the 'Third Wave'" 1995 (Box 5)
    - Bristol-Myers Squibb at Princeton, NJ 1995 (Box 5)
    - College of Engineering National Advisory Committee "University of Michigan Digital Library Initiatives" 1995 (Box 5)
    - Morino Institute / Kaye Gapin, Washington 1995 (Box 5)
    - ALA at Chicago -- Keynote speaker at Lib Research Roundtable "NSF/NASA/ARPA Funded Digital Library Projects" 1995 (Box 5)
    - European trip 1995 (Box 5)
    - NIST Strategic planning workshop on information "New knowledge work environments: Digital libraries and collaboratories" 1995 (Box 5)
    - US-EC Neuroinformatics Workshop "Electronic Collaboratories and Digital Libraries" 1995 (Box 5)
    - Virtual Library Project, Emory University, Atlanta 1995 (Box 5)
    - Tokyo: Kanazawa Institute of Technology International Roundtable 1995 (Box 5)
    - New York Public Library / John Seeley Brown 1995 (Box 5)
    - ALISE / ALA 1996 (Box 5)
    - Ontario Library Association Super Conference, Toronto 1996 (Box 5)
    - ALA / NSF Meeting 1996 (Box 5)
    - Faculty retreat 3 1996 (Box 5)
    - IBM "Executive briefing" 1996 (Box 5)
    - Springer -- Verlag: Heidelburg, Germany 1996 (Box 5)
    - Chancellor's Conference, Marburg, Germany 1996 (Box 5)
    - ALA in New York 1996 (Box 5)
    - Cathy Stone, Knollenberg's Staff 1996 (Box 5)
    - Swiss Federal Institute 1996 (Box 5)
    - Zensei Oshiro Dsohisha Univ. (Japan) 1996 (Box 5)
    - Library Initiative Meeting 1996 (Box 5)
    - Prudence Dalrymple, ALA 1996 (Box 5)
    - Special faculty recruitment meetings 1996 (Box 5)
    - NASA Information Infrastructure, Technology and Applications (IITA) Conference 1996 (Box 5)
    - Jose Marie Griffiths, Peter Noerr 1996 (Box 5)
    - Al Hammond 1996 (Box 5)
    - Barry Checkoway lunch 1996 (Box 5)
    - David Liddel 1996 (Box 5)
    - US-EU Neuroinformatics Steering Group Conference Call 1996 (Box 5)
    - Parents Weekend 1996 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Library Association (MLA) Keynote Speech 1996 (Box 5)
    - Mike Simmons visit 1996 (Box 5)
    - Private Univ. Sys. Research Group of Tokyo 1996 (Box 5)
    - DELOS Workshop, Bonn Germany 1996 (Box 5)
    - Ann Wolpert MIT Director of Libraries 1996 (Box 5)
    - Terabit forum 1996 (Box 5)
    - Collaboratory in undergraduate education 1996 (Box 6)
    - Tour of Lurie w/Steelcase Dedication of Lurie 1996 (Box 6)
    - ILLSA Officers Luncheon Meeting 1996 (Box 6)
    - Robert Warner Symposium 1996 (Box 6)
    - John Seeley Brown, Gail McClure meeting 1996 (Box 6)
    - ERCIM Meeting, Prague 1996 (Box 6)
    - Edward Brothers / JSTOR 1996 (Box 6)